Seventy-thousand years ago, our ancestors were insignificant animals.
منذ 70,000 عام مضت، كان أسلافنا عبارةً عن حيواناتٍ غير متميزة
The most important thing to know about prehistoric humans
النقطة الهامة للغاية التي يجب مراعاتها فيما يتعلق بإنسان ما قبل التاريخ
is that they were unimportant.
أنه كان غير مهم.
Their impact on the world was not much greater than that of jellyfish
ولم يكن تأثيره على الكوكب يتعدى تأثير قنديل البحر
or fireflies or woodpeckers.
أو اليراعات المضيئة، أو نقار الخشب.
Today, in contrast, we control this planet.
وبالمقابل، فنحن نسيطر على الكوكب اليوم.
And the question is:
والسؤال المطروح هو:
How did we come from there to here?
كيف تطورنا من تلك المرحلة حتى الآن؟
How did we turn ourselves from insignificant apes,
كيف حولنا أنفسنا من قرود غير متميزة،
minding their own business in a corner of Africa,
جل اهتمامها منصب في زاوية في افريقيا،
into the rulers of planet Earth?
إلى حكام لكوكب الأرض؟
Usually, we look for the difference between us and all the other animals
عادة، ما ننظر إلى الاختلافات بيننا وبين بقية الحيوانات
on the individual level.
على مستوىً فردي.
We want to believe -- I want to believe --
نريد أن نعتقد -- أريد أن أعتقد --
that there is something special about me,
بأن ثمة ما هو مميزٌ بشأني،
about my body, about my brain,
فيما يتعلق بجسدي، بدماغي،
that makes me so superior to a dog or a pig, or a chimpanzee.
هذا ما يجعلني أشد رقياً من الكلب، أو الخنزير، أو الشمبانزي.
But the truth is that, on the individual level,
إلا أن الحقيقة هي، وعلى المستوى الفردي،
I'm embarrassingly similar to a chimpanzee.
أنني وبشكلٍ محرجٍ مشابهٌ للشمبانزي.
And if you take me and a chimpanzee and put us together on some lonely island,
وإذا قمت بأخذي والشمبانزي ووضعتنا كلينا على إحدى الجزر الخاوية،
and we had to struggle for survival to see who survives better,
وتوجب علينا أن نصارع من أجل البقاء لرؤية من ينجو بشكل أفضل،
I would definitely place my bet on the chimpanzee, not on myself.
فإنني قطعاً سأراهن على الشمبانزي وليس على نفسي أنا.
And this is not something wrong with me personally.
وهذا ليس بسبب أمرٍ خاطئٍ خاصٍّ بي.
I guess if they took almost any one of you, and placed you alone
وأظن أن أياً منكم لو أُخذ ووُضع وحيداً
with a chimpanzee on some island,
مع الشمبانزي على إحدى الجزر،
the chimpanzee would do much better.
فإن الشمبانزي سيحسن صنعاً بشكلٍ أكبر بكثير.
The real difference between humans and all other animals
الاختلاف الجوهري بين الانسان وبقية الحيوانات جميعها
is not on the individual level;
لا يكمن على المستوى الفردي؛
it's on the collective level.
بل على المستوى الجماعي.
Humans control the planet because they are the only animals
البشر يتحكمون بالكوكب لأنهم الحيوانات الوحيدة
that can cooperate both flexibly and in very large numbers.
القادرة على التعاون بمرونة وعلى نطاقٍ كبيرٍ جداً كذلك.
Now, there are other animals --
الآن، يوجد حيواناتٌ أخرى --
like the social insects, the bees, the ants --
كالحشرات الاجتماعية، النحل، النمل --
that can cooperate in large numbers, but they don't do so flexibly.
بمقدورها العمل بأعدادٍ هائلةٍ، ولكن ليس بتلك المرونة.
Their cooperation is very rigid.
فتعاونها صارمٌ جداً.
There is basically just one way in which a beehive can function.
ويوجد بشكلٍ أساسيٍّ طريقةٌ واحدةٌ فقط يمكن لفريق النحل العمل بها.
And if there's a new opportunity or a new danger,
وعند توافر فرصةٍ جديدةٍ أو خطرٍ داهمٍ،
the bees cannot reinvent the social system overnight.
فلا يسع النحل إعادة هيكلة النظام في ليلة واحدة.
They cannot, for example, execute the queen
فلا يمكنها، على سبيل المثال إعدام الملكة
and establish a republic of bees,
و تأسيس جمهورية نحلٍ،
or a communist dictatorship of worker bees.
أو ديكتاتوريةٍ شيوعيةٍ من النحل العاملات.
Other animals, like the social mammals --
حيوانات أخرى، كالثديات الاجتماعية --
the wolves, the elephants, the dolphins, the chimpanzees --
الذئاب، الفيلة، الدلافين، الشمبانزي --
they can cooperate much more flexibly,
بإمكانها التعاون فيما بينها بشكلٍ أكثر مرونةً،
but they do so only in small numbers,
إلا أنها تفعل ذلك بأعدادٍ صغيرةٍ،
because cooperation among chimpanzees
لأن التعاون فيما بين قرود الشمبانزي
is based on intimate knowledge, one of the other.
قائمً على المعرفة الحميمة كلٌّ للآخر.
I'm a chimpanzee and you're a chimpanzee,
أنا قرد شمبانزي، وأنت قرد شمبانزي،
and I want to cooperate with you.
وأريد التعاون معك.
I need to know you personally.
فعلي أن أعرفك بشكلٍ شخصيٍّ.
What kind of chimpanzee are you?
أي نوعٍ من الشمبانزي أنت؟
Are you a nice chimpanzee?
هل أنت لطيف؟
Are you an evil chimpanzee?
أم شرير؟
Are you trustworthy?
هل أنت جديرٌ بالثقة؟
If I don't know you, how can I cooperate with you?
وإن كنت لا أعرفك، فكيف لي أن أتعاون معك؟
The only animal that can combine the two abilities together
الحيوان الوحيد القادر على دمج المقدرتين معاً
and cooperate both flexibly and still do so in very large numbers
والتعاون بمرونةٍ وعلى نطاق أعدادٍ كبيرةٍ جداً
is us, Homo sapiens.
هو نحن، الانسان العاقل.
One versus one, or even 10 versus 10,
واحد مقابل واحد، أو حتى 10 مقابل 10،
chimpanzees might be better than us.
قد تكون قرود الشمبانزي أفضل منا.
But, if you pit 1,000 humans against 1,000 chimpanzees,
ولكن، إن وضعت 1000 إنسان في مواجهة 1000 قرد شمبانزي،
the humans will win easily, for the simple reason
فإن البشر سيفوزون بسهولة، لسببٍ بسيطٍ
that a thousand chimpanzees cannot cooperate at all.
وهو أن قرود الشمبانزي الألف لن يكون بمقدورها العمل جماعةً على الإطلاق.
And if you now try to cram 100,000 chimpanzees
وإن كنت ستحاول جمع 100,000 قرد شمبانزي
into Oxford Street, or into Wembley Stadium,
داخل شارع أوكسفورد، أو في ملعب ويمبلي،
or Tienanmen Square or the Vatican,
أو في ساحة السلام السماوي أو ساحة الفاتيكان،
you will get chaos, complete chaos.
فستحصل على فوضى، فوضى عارمة.
Just imagine Wembley Stadium with 100,000 chimpanzees.
تخيل فقط ملعب ويمبلي وفيه 100,000 قرد من الشمبانزي.
Complete madness.
جنونٌ كلي.
In contrast, humans normally gather there in tens of thousands,
وبالمقابل، فإن البشر بشكلٍ طبيعيٍّ يتجمعون بعشرات الألاف،
and what we get is not chaos, usually.
وما نحصل عليه ليس الفوضى، عادةً.
What we get is extremely sophisticated and effective networks of cooperation.
ما نحصل عليه هو شبكة تعاونٍ فعالةٍ ومعقدةٍ بشكلٍ هائل.
All the huge achievements of humankind throughout history,
جميع الانجازات العظيمة للجنس البشري عبر التاريخ،
whether it's building the pyramids or flying to the moon,
سواء كانت بناء الأهرامات، أو الوصول للقمر،
have been based not on individual abilities,
تمت ليس بفضل المقدرات الفردية،
but on this ability to cooperate flexibly in large numbers.
بل تمت بهذه القدرة على التعاون بمرونةٍ بأعدادٍ هائلة.
Think even about this very talk that I'm giving now:
تمعنوا حتى في هذه المحاضرة التي ألقيها الآن:
I'm standing here in front of an audience of about 300 or 400 people,
أقف هنا أمام الجمهور مكون من 300 أو 400 شخص،
most of you are complete strangers to me.
معظمكم هم غرباء بالنسبة لي تماماً.
Similarly, I don't really know all the people who have organized
بالمثل، فأني لا أعرف حقاً جميع الأشخاص الذين نظموا
and worked on this event.
وعملوا على هذا الحدث.
I don't know the pilot and the crew members of the plane
أنا لا أعرف الطيار وأعضاء الطاقم على الطائرة
that brought me over here, yesterday, to London.
التي حطت بي هنا البارحة قادماً إلى لندن.
I don't know the people who invented and manufactured
أنا لا أعرف الأشخاص الذين صمموا وصنعوا
this microphone and these cameras, which are recording what I'm saying.
هذا الميكروفون وهذه الكاميرا، والتي تسجل ما أقوله.
I don't know the people who wrote all the books and articles
لا أعرف الأشخاص الذين كتبوا جميع الكتب والمقالات
that I read in preparation for this talk.
والتي قرأتها تحضيراً لهذه المحاضرة.
And I certainly don't know all the people
ومؤكد لا أعرف جميع الأشخاص
who might be watching this talk over the Internet,
الذين قد يشاهدون هذه المحاضرة على شبكة الانترنت.
somewhere in Buenos Aires or in New Delhi.
في مكانٍ ما في بيونس آيرس، نيو دلهي.
Nevertheless, even though we don't know each other,
ومع ذلك، وبالرغم من عدم معرفتنا ببعضنا البعض،
we can work together to create this global exchange of ideas.
إلا أنه في مقدورنا ابتكار هذا الخليط العالمي من الأفكار.
This is something chimpanzees cannot do.
هذا أمر لا يمكن لقرود الشمبانزي إنجازه.
They communicate, of course,
بالطبع هي تستطيع التواصل،
but you will never catch a chimpanzee traveling to some distant chimpanzee band
ولكن لن تعثر على قرد شمبانزي يسافر إلى جماعة شمبانزي بعيدة
to give them a talk about bananas or about elephants,
ليلقي عليهم محاضرة عن الموز، أو عن الفيلة.
or anything else that might interest chimpanzees.
أو بخصوص أي موضوع يثير اهتمام قرود الشمبانزي.
Now cooperation is, of course, not always nice;
بالطبع، ليس جميع أشكال التعاون محمودة؛
all the horrible things humans have been doing throughout history --
فجميع الأشياء الرهيبة التي قام الانسان بها عبر التاريخ --
and we have been doing some very horrible things --
والأمور الرهيبة التي لا زلنا نقوم بها --
all those things are also based on large-scale cooperation.
جميع هذه الأمور استندت على عنصر التعاون على نطاق واسع جداً.
Prisons are a system of cooperation;
السجون هي نظام تعاون؛
slaughterhouses are a system of cooperation;
المسالخ هي نظام تعاون؛
concentration camps are a system of cooperation.
معسكرات الاعتقال هي نظام تعاون.
Chimpanzees don't have slaughterhouses and prisons and concentration camps.
قرود الشمبانزي لا تمتلك مسالخ وسجون ومعسكرات اعتقال.
Now suppose I've managed to convince you perhaps that yes,
الآن لنفترض أني أحاول إقناعكم بإمكانية أنه صحيح،
we control the world because we can cooperate flexibly in large numbers.
نحن نتحكم بالعالم لأنه بمقدورنا العمل معاً بمرونةٍ وبأعدادٍ كبيرة.
The next question that immediately arises
إلا أن السؤال التالي الذي يبرز مباشرةً
in the mind of an inquisitive listener is:
في عقل مستمعٍ فضوليٍّ وهو:
How, exactly, do we do it?
كيف نقوم بهذا الأمر على وجه التحديد؟
What enables us alone, of all the animals, to cooperate in such a way?
ما الذي يجعلنا قادرين وحدنا، من بين جميع الحيوانات على التعاون بالشكل الذي نقوم به؟
The answer is our imagination.
الجواب هو مخيلتنا.
We can cooperate flexibly with countless numbers of strangers,
يمكننا العمل معاً بمرونة مع عدد لا يحصى من الغرباء،
because we alone, of all the animals on the planet,
لأننا من دون سائر الحيوانات على الكوكب،
can create and believe fictions, fictional stories.
يمكننا ابتكار وتصديق الخيال، القصص الخيالية.
And as long as everybody believes in the same fiction,
وطالما آمن كل واحدٍ بنفس الخيال،
everybody obeys and follows the same rules,
فكل واحدٍ عندها سيذعن ويتبع نفس الأحكام،
the same norms, the same values.
نفس السنن، ونفس القيم.
All other animals use their communication system
جميع الحيوانات الأخرى تستخدم نظاماً للتواصل
only to describe reality.
من أجل وصف الواقع فقط.
A chimpanzee may say, "Look! There's a lion, let's run away!"
فقرد شمبانزي قد يقول، "انظر! ثمة أسد، لنهرب بعيداً!"
Or, "Look! There's a banana tree over there! Let's go and get bananas!"
أو، "انظر! توجد شجرة موزٍ هنالك! لنذهب ونحصل على موز!"
Humans, in contrast, use their language not merely to describe reality,
البشر في المقابل، يستخدمون لغاتهم ليس فقط من أجل وصف الواقع،
but also to create new realities, fictional realities.
بل من أجل ابتكار واقعٍ جديدٍ، واقعٍ خياليٍّ.
A human can say, "Look, there is a god above the clouds!
إنسان ما يمكنه أن يقول، "انظر، ثمة إلهٌ فوق الغيوم!
And if you don't do what I tell you to do,
وإن لم تفعل ما آمرك به،
when you die, God will punish you and send you to hell."
فعندما تموت، سيعاقبك الرب، ويرسلك إلى الجحيم."
And if you all believe this story that I've invented,
وإن صدقتم جميعكم هذه القصة التي ابتكرتها للتو،
then you will follow the same norms and laws and values,
عندها ستتبعون نفس السنن والقوانين والقيم،
and you can cooperate.
وستتمكنون من التعاون.
This is something only humans can do.
هذا أمرٌ يستطيع البشر وحدهم فعله.
You can never convince a chimpanzee to give you a banana
لن تستطيع البتة إقناع قرد شمبانزي بإعطائك موزة
by promising him, "... after you die, you'll go to chimpanzee heaven ..."
عن طريق وعده، "بعد موتك، ستذهب إلى جنة الشمبانزي..."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"... and you'll receive lots and lots of bananas for your good deeds.
"...و ستحصل على الكثير و الكثير من الموز جزاءً لأفعالك الحسنة
So now give me this banana."
لذلك أعطني هذه الموزة الآن."
No chimpanzee will ever believe such a story.
لن يصدق أي قرد شمبانزي هذه القصة على الاطلاق.
Only humans believe such stories,
وحدهم البشر يصدقون قصصاً مماثلة،
which is why we control the world,
وهنا هو السبب وراء تحكمنا بالعالم،
whereas the chimpanzees are locked up in zoos and research laboratories.
فيما يقبع قرود الشمبانزي في حدائق الحيوانات ومخابر البحث العلمي.
Now you may find it acceptable that yes,
الآن قد تجد من المقبول أنه نعم،
in the religious field, humans cooperate by believing in the same fictions.
في النطاق الديني، البشر يتعاونون عن طريق الإيمان بنفس القصص التخيلية.
Millions of people come together to build a cathedral or a mosque
فملايين البشر يجتمعون سوياً لبناء كاتدرائية أو مسجدٍ
or fight in a crusade or a jihad, because they all believe in the same stories
أو ليحاربوا بحملاتٍ صليبيةٍ أو جهاديةٍ، لأنهم جميعاً يؤمنون بنفس القصص
about God and heaven and hell.
المتعلقة بالرب والجنة والنار.
But what I want to emphasize is that exactly the same mechanism
ولكن ما أود التشديد عليه هو أن ذات الآلية تماماً
underlies all other forms of mass-scale human cooperation,
تكمن وراء جميع الأشكال الأخرى من التعاون البشري على النطاق الهائل،
not only in the religious field.
وليس فقط في الحقل الديني.
Take, for example, the legal field.
خذ على سبيل المثال، الحقل القانوني.
Most legal systems today in the world are based on a belief in human rights.
معظم الأنظمة التشريعية اليوم في العالم تقوم على أساس الإيمان بحقوق الإنسان.
But what are human rights?
ولكن ماهي حقوق الإنسان؟
Human rights, just like God and heaven, are just a story that we've invented.
حقوق الإنسان، هي تماما كالإله والجنة، قصةٌ قمنا بابتكارها.
They are not an objective reality;
فهي ليست حقائق موضوعية؛
they are not some biological effect about homo sapiens.
وهي ليست تأثيراً عضوياً ما على الإنسان العاقل
Take a human being, cut him open, look inside,
خذ إنساناً، افتحه وانظر بداخله،
you will find the heart, the kidneys, neurons, hormones, DNA,
ستجدون القلب، الكليتين، الخلايا العصبية، الهرمونات، DNA،
but you won't find any rights.
لكنكم لن تجدوا أي حقوق.
The only place you find rights are in the stories
المكان الوحيد الذي ستجدون فيه الحقوق هو في القصص
that we have invented and spread around over the last few centuries.
التي قمنا بابتكارها ونشرها في كل مكان خلال القرون القليلة الماضية.
They may be very positive stories, very good stories,
قد تكون تلك القصص إيجابية جداً، وجيدةً جداً،
but they're still just fictional stories that we've invented.
إلا أنها تبقى قصصاً خياليةً ابتكرناها.
The same is true of the political field.
الأمر هو ذاته فيما يتعلق بالحقل السياسي.
The most important factors in modern politics are states and nations.
العناصر الأكثر أهمية في السياسة المعاصرة هي الدول والأمم.
But what are states and nations?
ولكن ماهي الدول والأمم؟
They are not an objective reality.
هي ليست عبارةً عن واقعٍ موضوعيٍّ.
A mountain is an objective reality.
الجبل هو واقعٌ موضوعي.
You can see it, you can touch it, you can even smell it.
يمكنك رؤيته، ولمسه، بل ويمكنك شمه.
But a nation or a state,
ولكن الأمم والدول،
like Israel or Iran or France or Germany,
كإسرائيل وإيران وفرنسا وألمانيا،
this is just a story that we've invented
ماهي إلا قصصٌ ابتكرناها بأنفسنا
and became extremely attached to.
وأصبحنا مرتبطين بها بعمق.
The same is true of the economic field.
الأمر ينطبق على الحقل الاقتصادي.
The most important actors today in the global economy
فأكثر العوامل أهمية في بناء الاقتصاد العالمي اليوم
are companies and corporations.
هي الشركات العملاقة.
Many of you today, perhaps, work for a corporation,
جلُّكم اليوم، ربما، يعمل لدى شركة،
like Google or Toyota or McDonald's.
كشركة غوغل أو تويوتا أو ماكدونالدز.
What exactly are these things?
ماهي بالتحديد هذه الأشياء؟
They are what lawyers call legal fictions.
هي عبارة عما يطلق عليه رجال القانون اسم الحيل القانونية.
They are stories invented and maintained
هي عبارةٌ عن قصصٍ تم ابتكارها والمحافظة عليها
by the powerful wizards we call lawyers.
عن طريق سحرة ذوو نفوذٍ ندعوهم برجال القانون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what do corporations do all day?
وما الذي تحاول تلك الشركات فعله طوال اليوم؟
Mostly, they try to make money.
غالباً، جني المال.
Yet, what is money?
مع ذلك، ما هو المال؟
Again, money is not an objective reality; it has no objective value.
مجدداً، المال ليس حقيقةً موضوعيةً، لا يملك قيمةً موضوعية.
Take this green piece of paper, the dollar bill.
خذ قطعة الورق الخضراء هذه، ورقة الدولار.
Look at it -- it has no value.
انظر إليها -- لا تملك أي قيمة.
You cannot eat it, you cannot drink it,
لا يمكنك أكلها، ولاشربها،
you cannot wear it.
ولا ارتداؤها.
But then came along these master storytellers --
ولكن فيما بعد، جاء هؤلاء الرواة المهرة --
the big bankers,
المصرفيون الكبار،
the finance ministers,
وزراء الاقتصاد،
the prime ministers --
رؤساء الوزراء --
and they tell us a very convincing story:
وأخبرونا قصةً شديدة الإقناع:
"Look, you see this green piece of paper?
"انظر، هل ترى قطعة الورق الخضراء هذه؟
It is actually worth 10 bananas."
في الواقع هذه تساوي 10 حبات موز."
And if I believe it, and you believe it,
وإن آمنت أنا بهذا، وأنت بهذا،
and everybody believes it,
والجميع صدقوا هذا،
it actually works.
عندها سيتم الأمر.
I can take this worthless piece of paper,
يمكنني أخذ قطعة الورق التافهة هذه،
go to the supermarket,
وأن أمضي للسوق،
give it to a complete stranger whom I've never met before,
أعطيها لشخص غريب عني تماماً، لم أقابله قطّ في حياتي،
and get, in exchange, real bananas which I can actually eat.
وآخذ، في المقابل، حبات موزٍ حقيقيةٍ يمكنني أكلها فعلاً.
This is something amazing.
هذا أمرٌ رائع.
You could never do it with chimpanzees.
فما كان بإمكانك مطلقاً فعل هذا الأمر مع الشمبانزي.
Chimpanzees trade, of course:
قرود الشمبانزي تتاجر بالطبع:
"Yes, you give me a coconut, I'll give you a banana."
"نعم، أنت تعطيني حبة جوز الهند، وسأعطيك موزةً."
That can work.
يمكن لهذا أن يتم،
But, you give me a worthless piece of paper
ولكن، أن تعطيني قطعة ورقةٍ تافهةٍ
and you except me to give you a banana?
وتتوقع مني أن أعطيك موزة؟
No way!
محال!
What do you think I am, a human?
ماذا تظنني، إنساناً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Money, in fact, is the most successful story
المال، في الحقيقة هو من أكثر القصص رواجاً
ever invented and told by humans,
والتي تم ابتكارها وتداولها من قبل البشر،
because it is the only story everybody believes.
لأنها القصة الوحيدة التي يؤمن بها الجميع.
Not everybody believes in God,
فلا يؤمن الجميع بالإله،
not everybody believes in human rights,
ولا يؤمن الجميع بحقوق الإنسان،
not everybody believes in nationalism,
ولا يؤمن الجميع بالقومية،
but everybody believes in money, and in the dollar bill.
إلا أن الجميع يؤمنون بالمال، وبورقة الدولار.
Take, even, Osama Bin Laden.
خذ حتى، أسامة بن لادن،
He hated American politics and American religion
كان يمقت السياسات الأمريكية والتدين الأمريكي
and American culture,
والثقافة الأمريكية،
but he had no objection to American dollars.
ولكن لم يكن له اعتراضٌ على الدولارات الأمريكية.
He was quite fond of them, actually.
كان مولعاً كلياً بها، في الواقع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To conclude, then:
إذا وللختام:
We humans control the world because we live in a dual reality.
نحن البشر نتحكم بالعالم لأننا نعيش في واقعٍ مزدوج.
All other animals live in an objective reality.
جميع الحيوانات الأخرى تعيش في عالمٍ موضوعي.
Their reality consists of objective entities,
حيث يتألف واقعها من كينوناتٍ موضوعية،
like rivers and trees and lions and elephants.
مثل أنهارٍ وأشجارٍ وأسودٍ وفيلة.
We humans, we also live in an objective reality.
نحن البشر، كذلك نعيش في عالمٍ موضوعي.
In our world, too, there are rivers and trees and lions and elephants.
في عالمنا أيضاً، يوجد أنهارٌ وأشجارٌ وأسودٌ وفيلة.
But over the centuries,
ولكن بمرور العصور،
we have constructed on top of this objective reality
قمنا ببناء طبقةٍ ثانيةٍ من الواقع الخيالي،
a second layer of fictional reality,
فوق الطبقة الأولى وهي الواقع الموضوعي
a reality made of fictional entities,
واقعٌ عناصره هي كينوناتٌ خيالية،
like nations, like gods, like money, like corporations.
مثل الأمم، الآلهة، المال، والشركات.
And what is amazing is that as history unfolded,
والمذهل هو أنه وبمرور الأزمنة والعصور،
this fictional reality became more and more powerful
فإن هذا الواقع الخيالي يصبح أكثر نفوذا
so that today, the most powerful forces in the world
اليوم ومن أجل ذلك، تعتبر أشد القوى الموجودة في العالم
are these fictional entities.
هي هذه الكينونات الخيالية.
Today, the very survival of rivers and trees and lions and elephants
اليوم، بقاء الأنهار والأشجار والأسود والفيلة على قيد الحياة
depends on the decisions and wishes of fictional entities,
يعتمد على القرارات والأمنيات الخاصة بالكينونات الخيالية،
like the United States, like Google, like the World Bank --
كالولايات المتحدة، كغوغل، كالبنك الدولي --
entities that exist only in our own imagination.
كينوناتٌ موجودةٌ فقط في مخيلاتنا.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Yuval, you have a new book out.
برونو جيوساني: يوفال، أصدرت كتاباً مؤخراً
After Sapiens, you wrote another one,
ما بعد الإنسان العاقل، قمت بتأليف كتابٍ آخر،
and it's out in Hebrew, but not yet translated into ...
وقد صدر باللغة العبرية، ولكنه لم يترجم بعد إلى ...
Yuval Noah Harari: I'm working on the translation as we speak.
يوفال نواه حراري: أعمل على ترجمته الآن.
BG: In the book, if I understand it correctly,
برونو جيوساني: في الكتاب، إن كنت قد فهمته بشكلٍ صحيح،
you argue that the amazing breakthroughs that we are experiencing right now
أثرت الجدل بأن الانجازات المذهلة التي نختبرها حالياً
not only will potentially make our lives better,
لن يكون بمقدورها تحسين حياتنا فقط
but they will create -- and I quote you --
بل ستخلق -- وأقتبس منك --
"... new classes and new class struggles, just as the industrial revolution did."
"...فئاتٍ و صراعاتٍ فئوية جديدة، تماماً كما فعلت الثورة الصناعية."
Can you elaborate for us?
هلّا فصلت لنا؟
YNH: Yes. In the industrial revolution,
يوفال نواه حراري: خلال الثورة الصناعية،
we saw the creation of a new class of the urban proletariat.
رأينا نشوء فئاتٍ عماليةٍ مدنية.
And much of the political and social history of the last 200 years involved
ومعظم التاريخ السياسي والاجتماعي للسنوات ال 200 الماضية ارتبطت
what to do with this class, and the new problems and opportunities.
عميقاً بهذه الفئة، وبالمشاكل والفرص الجديدة.
Now, we see the creation of a new massive class of useless people.
اليوم، نشاهد نشوء فئةٍ كبيرةٍ جداً من الناس المهملين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As computers become better and better in more and more fields,
نظراً لدخول الحواسيب مجالاتٍ كثيرةٍ متعددةٍ وتحسن أدائها،
there is a distinct possibility that computers will out-perform us
يوجد إمكانيةٌ كبيرةٌ لأن تقوم الحواسيب بتعطيلنا عن العمل
in most tasks and will make humans redundant.
في معظم المهام وستجعل العنصر البشري لحالات الاحتياط.
And then the big political and economic question
وعندها سيكون السؤال السياسي والاقتصادي الهام
of the 21st century will be,
للقرن الحادي والعشرين،
"What do we need humans for?",
"فيما سنحتاج البشر؟"
or at least, "What do we need so many humans for?"
أو على الأقل، "ما الداعي للكثير من البشر؟"
BG: Do you have an answer in the book?
برونو جيوساني: هل أجبت عن السؤال في الكتاب؟
YNH: At present, the best guess we have is to keep them happy
يوفال نواه حراري: حالياً، أفضل تخمين لدينا هو أن نبقيهم سعداء
with drugs and computer games ...
بالمخدرات وألعاب الحاسوب...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but this doesn't sound like a very appealing future.
لكن هذا لا يبدو مستقبلاً مشرقاً.
BG: Ok, so you're basically saying in the book and now,
برونو جيوساني: حسنٌ، إذاً أنت تقول بشكلٍ أساسيٍّ في الكتاب وهنا،
that for all the discussion about the growing evidence
أنه من أجل كل النقاش حول الدليل المتصاعد بشأن
of significant economic inequality, we are just kind of at the beginning
عدم المساواة الاقتصادية الواضحة،
of the process?
أننا في بداية العملية؟
YNH: Again, it's not a prophecy;
يوفال نواه حراري: مجدداً، هذه ليست نبوءة؛
it's seeing all kinds of possibilities before us.
تبرز جميع الاحتمالات أمامنا.
One possibility is this creation of a new massive class of useless people.
أحد الاحتمالات هو نشوء هذه الفئة الجديدة من العدد الكبير من الناس العاطلين عن العمل.
Another possibility is the division of humankind
احتمالٌ أخر هو تقسيم الجنس البشري
into different biological castes,
إلى أعراق حيوية،
with the rich being upgraded into virtual gods,
حيث سيرتقي من خلاله الأثرياء إلى رتبة آلهة مفترضة،
and the poor being degraded to this level of useless people.
والفقراء سيهوون إلى رتبة الحثالة.
BG: I feel there is another TED talk coming up in a year or two.
برونو: أشعر بأن لديك محاضرةً أخرى في TED خلال سنة أو سنتين قادمتين
Thank you, Yuval, for making the trip.
شكراً لك، يوفال على قيامك بالرحلة.
YNH: Thanks!
يوفال نواه حراري: شكراً!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)